בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is דף ס, Daf Samech,
60, but we start at the very bottom of נט עמוד א.
Nun Tet Amud Aleph. We're a little bit behind and
based on a question of why does the תורה Torah have to
repeat the prohibition of אבר מן החי Ever Min Hachai or דם
מן החי Dam Min Hachai once it was already included in בני
נח. Bnei Noach. The גמרא Gemara says it's a very important principle
which is also very bizarre, which is that anything that was said
to בני נח Bnei Noach and repeated, it applies to both. Okay,
that makes sense. But then it says anything that was only said
to בני נח Bnei Noach and not repeated, it only applies to
ישראל. Yisrael. And therefore, אבר מן החי Ever Min Hachai had to
be repeated so that it applies to both. All right, and
so we pick up, and that the only thing that was said
only to בני נח Bnei Noach and not repeated and therefore applies
only to ישראל Yisrael is גיד הנשה, Gid Hanashe, which is itself
a little bizarre because that's explicit. It says על כן לא יאכלו
בני ישראל. Al Ken Lo Yochlu Bnei Yisrael. Okay, but anyway we'll
see, the גמרא Gemara will continue to explore what falls in these
categories. But we pick up with the גמרא Gemara analyzing the second
half of that at the bottom of נט עמוד א. Nun Tet
Amud Aleph. ולבני נח ולא נשנית בסיני לישראל נאמרה ולא לבני נח.
U'l'Bnei Noach v'lo nishnah b'Sinai, l'Yisrael ne'emra v'lo l'Bnei Noach. It was
said to בני נח Bnei Noach and not repeated,
it only applies to Jews. אדרבה, Aderaba, the גמרא Gemara asks the
obvious question: דלא נשנית בסיני לבני נח נאמרה ולא לישראל? D'lo nishnas
b'Sinai l'Bnei Noach ne'emra v'lo l'Yisrael? Let's say the fact that it
wasn't repeated at הר סיני Har Sinai means it was only said
to בני נח Bnei Noach and not to בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael.
So there would be a whole category of things that would not
apply to בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael that would only apply to בני
נח. Bnei Noach. So the גמרא Gemara says no, and here's a
principle that we've seen before: ליכא מידי דלישראל שרי ולעכו"ם אסור. Leika
mida d'l'Yisrael sharei u'l'Akum assur. There is nothing that could be permitted
to a Jew that's forbidden to a non-Jew. Non-Jews are also Jews
are also in the human category. So if it's prohibited to בני
נח, Bnei Noach, it would have to also be prohibited to Jews
as well. Or the phrase the גמרא Gemara used before: we're going
to a higher level of קדושה, kedusha, we have to assume that
things become more prohibited and there's nothing that could be prohibited for
בני נח Bnei Noach and מותר mutar for us. So if it
was only said to בני נח Bnei Noach and not for us,
rather than saying that it only applies to them and not us,
we say the reverse: it applies to us and not to them.
But now the גמרא Gemara questions it. Is this really true that
there's nothing that's forbidden to them and permissible to us? The גמרא
Gemara says ולא, v'lo, is there not? והרי יפת תואר. Ve'harei Yefat
To'ar. How about יפת תואר? Yefat To'ar? We said before that that
for them was under the גזל gezel category and we know the
תורה Torah permits for us יפת תואר. Yefat To'ar. גמרא Gemara says
התם משום דלאו בני כיבוש נינהו. hasam mishum d'lav bnei kibush ninhu.
That's because there's not a concept of the mechanism... it's very interesting...
the mechanism of that when you conquer a foreign land, it becomes
yours and you own it legally, that applies to wars that בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael fight but not wars that the gentiles fight. So
therefore it wouldn't be גזל. gezel. Why is it גזל? gezel? You've
conquered that nation, they're yours. But so that's why it's okay for
ישראל. Yisrael. For non-Jew, the reason it's not okay is not that
in principle they wouldn't be entitled to it if they owned it,
it's just the mechanism isn't there because they don't own the land
that they conquer. Which is by the way very strange because the
גמרא Gemara says, besides that it's bizarre that that should be true,
but anyway, like the reason that בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael could conquer
עבר הירדן Ever HaYarden and settle in lands that once belonged to
עמון Amon and מואב Moav was because when סיחון Sichon conquered it,
it became סיחון's, Sichon it stopped being עמון Amon and מואב. Moav.
Anyway, that's the answer the גמרא Gemara gives for that.
Meaning they're just defining a problem with the mechanism, not really the
concept? Exactly. והרי. v'harei.
Doesn't the תורה Torah say that when...? Yeah, I mean you're right.
There are explicit verses in the תורה. Torah. God gave it to
them. God says and I gave it to them, right exactly. Yeah,
so it's very hard to understand what it means ואבני כיבוש נינהו.
v'avnei kibush ninhu.
I don't know what to say about that. You're right, it's ממש
mamash explicit in the תורה. Torah. Okay. והרי פחות משוה פרוטה? V'harei
pachos mi'shaveh prutah? How about less than a פרוטה? prutah? We said
that that was אסור asur to בני נח Bnei Noach and it's
מותר mutar for ישראל. Yisrael. So the גמרא Gemara said no, התם
משום דלאו בני מחילה נינהו. hasam mishum d'lav bnei mechila ninhu. Really
it's אסור asur to ישראל Yisrael as well. It's just that when
somebody steals from us less than a פרוטה, prutah, we're מוחל. mochel.
If somebody steals from them less than a פרוטה, prutah, whatever, they're
not מוחל. mochel. So there's no real difference, it's just whether you
have the fact of
מחילה mechila to sort of make it to change the nature of
what happened.
Okay. If you look at רש"י, Rashi, משום דלאו בני מחילה נינהו
דאף ישראל נצטוו על הגזל. mishum d'lav bnei mechila ninhu, d'af Yisrael
nitztavu al hagezel. Well, that would be a different answer.
Fundamentally the thing applies, the details can be different. That's not what
the גמרא Gemara is saying. It's saying אלא דפחות משוה פרוטה אינו
נחשב גזל בעיניהם שעוברים
מדתן
שרחמנים הם ומוחלין על דבר קל. ela d'pachos mi'shaveh prutah eino nechshav
gezel b'ei'neihem, she'ovrim midasan, she'rachamim hem, u'mochlin al davar kal. If they
weren't מוחל mochel it would be גזל. gezel. It only stops being
גזל gezel because they're מוחל. mochel. Okay, אבל בני נח אסורים הם.
aval Bnei Noach asurim hem. So it's but by בני נח Bnei
Noach since you don't have that reality of מחילה. mechila. Now look
at תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot asks an important thing because if you
remember, one of the areas of difference, I sort of said there's
an idea maybe of more שיעורים shiurim by בני נח... Bnei Noach.
by ישראל Yisrael than בני נח. Bnei Noach So one area where
you don't have a שיעור shiur by בני נח bnei noach, is
the amount of money, even less than a פרוטה, prutah, but the
other area is abortion, that even a... A fetus is considered still
alive, whereas for Jews in הלכה halacha it's not considered a full
life for the issues, it wouldn't be considered murder. Okay, so look
at תוספות, Tosfos, תוספות Tosfos asks why didn't the גמרא Gemara ask
about that
issue. ליכא מידי דלישראל שרי ובדבר שהוא מצווה לישראל לא אמרינן הכי.
Leka midam de'Yisrael shari u'bedavar she'hu mitzvah le'Yisrael lo amrinan hachi. הוה
ליה כעובד כוכבים ששבת חייב ולישראל מצווה. Hovei lei ke'ovad kochavim sheshavat
chayiv u'le'Yisrael mitzvah. So why don't you say that's something that
is forbidden for them to take a rest day on שבת Shabbos
and it's permissible for us? No, it's not permissible for us, it's
a מצווה mitzvah for us. Anyway, the whole שבת Shabbos thing is
obviously a little bit not the normal part of the list. Okay.
אף על גב דבשינוי בשבת אין מצווה לישראל מכל מקום יש בה
מצווה ששבת. Af al gav de'beshinui be'Shabbos ein mitzvah le'Yisrael mikol makom
yesh bah mitzvah sheshavat. Okay, so that's not a question of is
it permitted or forbidden. That's a question when we're מצווה metzuve to
do something that obviously puts us at a higher level of קדושה.
kedusha. מכל מקום Mikol makom but now תוספות Tosfos asks this question:
והעוברים דעובדי כוכבים חייב ובישראל פטור. Ve'haubrin de'ovdei kochavim chayiv u've'Yisrael patur.
Now how about that? For them it's murder in terms of abortion
and for us we're exempt. ישראל פטור. Yisrael patur. אף על גב
Af al gav it's not even פטור, patur, it's אסור, assur, right?
Well, I'll get to that. אף על גב דפטור מכל מקום לא
שרי. Af al gav de'patur mikol makom lo shari. So תוספות Tosfos
says okay, but when we said there's nothing that's forbidden to them
and permissible to us, we don't mean that it's like totally permissible.
As
long as it's not totally permissible. There might be things that are
forbidden for them and they're less weighty for us. For them it's
considered murder, for us it's not considered murder, okay, but that doesn't
mean that it's actually permitted. Okay, and therefore that's why the גמרא
Gemara does not raise that issue. Okay, so now this point that
תוספות Tosfos says that abortion, his way of solving this problem
is that it's not permitted, right? And presumably the פשט pshat of
that would presumably be that it's not permitted even דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, even
biblically speaking. Because some want to say the whole problem of abortion
within הלכה halacha would be only a רבנן rabbinic problem. But if
it were only a רבנן rabbinic problem, it wouldn't solve the conceptual
point that how could it be that they're more prohibited than we
are? It would seem that within that that it's prohibited at a
דאורייתא d'Oraisa level. The גמרא Gemara is not asking the question, it
means it only is prohibited דרבנן? d'Rabbanan? No, if it were only
prohibited דרבנן d'Rabbanan then it would be a problem. Then there'd be
something that's fundamentally prohibited to them and fundamentally permissible to us until
the רבנים Rabbis came along and made it forbidden. Right, so if
you want to say that the basic structure is that the תורה
Torah would never make something forbidden to them and totally permissible to
us, and the answer's well abortion is also forbidden for us. It
seems like we're saying the תורה's Torah forbidden. Okay, now it could
be someone to say that this idea there's nothing forbidden to them
and permissible to us is not like a principle of the structure
of the system. It's more like the רבנים Rabbis wouldn't allow it,
that you shouldn't think like we saw
before, it's easier in some ways being a Jew. Although I do
have to tell you a story that somebody once was in the
process of conversion and they were coming from a very strict Christian
background and they wanted to know, I forget how this came up,
but they wanted to know, oh, like is it allowed for you
to read Harry Potter? Because it has all this magic in it.
I said, yeah, yeah, that's okay. She says, whoa, you guys are
so lenient! So anyway,
so it could be it's a דרבנן d'Rabbanan concern that it doesn't
look more lenient and then it could be solved by a דרבנן
d'Rabbanan edict. But it seems like it's more of a structural issue
that the תורה Torah would never create less have Jews in the
less sort of weighty position than non-Jews. So if that's true, the
idea that תוספות Tosfos says that abortion is still forbidden would mean
it's still forbidden at some תורה Torah level. Now that doesn't mean
that it's considered murder. The most extreme position on abortion is רב
משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein who says that basically it's murder without
the death penalty associated with it. Okay, just saying it's forbidden, even
saying it's forbidden דאורייתא d'Oraisa could be a completely different category. Alright,
so those are the questions around abortion. I will say there's another
תוספות Tosfos in discussing this issue that when he discusses abortion rather
than saying פטור patur says מותר. mutar. And רב משה פיינשטיין Rav
Moshe Feinstein is
so can't deal with that in any way and he says it
must be a טעות סופר, ta'us sofer, it's got to be פטור,
patur, not מותר. mutar. Okay, but anyway, but there is a תוספות
Tosfos that says מותר. mutar. מותר Mutar for us? מותר Mutar for
us, yeah. Anyway. Is there any concept associated what we've had that
before where it's not murder
here that you're not דווקא שאין davka she'ein death penalty? Right, that's
what רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein says. Yeah, essentially, that's what
רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein says, it's just an exemption from
the execution, but many others take a much more lenient approach. Okay,
so for them we're all agreeing though whatever side we say for
us whether it's permitted or somewhat prohibited, it's actually אסור assur on
death penalty for them. Correct, correct. Any point? But yes, correct. Even
like so that's the question is there any minimum amount 40 less
than 40 days morning after pill? Right, I don't know, that's not
clear. I would assume that still it's not even considered an עובר
ubar in the rabbinic language until after 40 days. So but it's
not yet even אדם באדם, adam ba'adam, but it's a good question
what is the minimum amount? Has that not been dealt with? Right,
well not practically since when we're... we ever judge בני נח, bnei
Noach although, you know, the Catholic Church because Catholic Church interprets the
פסוק pasuk which says,
it says, if somebody hits, you know, a woman, a man hits
a woman, you know, and it says ולא יהיה אסון v'lo yihiyeh
ason and there's no אסון, ason, then he's punished and he has
to pay, you know, whatever, a certain amount to the, to the
father. So the Septuagint translated the words אסון ason meaning not that
there's no, you know, tragedy that there wasn't a, that the woman
didn't die or whatever, it translates the words אסון ason as the
child was not yet formed. And therefore based on that Septuagint translation,
the Catholic Church has understood that once the child is formed, it
would be considered murder. I don't know what the שיעור shiur is
for that of what's considered formed. But anyway, but it's a good
point, like, is there some minimum? Anyway, I just want to finish
the rest of this תוספות Tosafot which raises another important issue. He
says, ומיהו קשיא דאמרינן בפרק בן סורר ומורה יצא ראשו אין נוגעין
בו דאין דוחין נפש מפני נפש, u'mihu kashya d'amrinan b'perek Ben Sorer
u'Moreh yatza rosho ein nogin bo d'ein dochin nefesh mipnei nefesh,
that once the baby's head emerges, you can't give up the baby's
life to save the mother. אבל קודם שיצא ראשו פושט ידו ומחתכו
לאיברים ומוציאו כדי להציל את אמו. aval kodem she'yatza rosho poshet yado
u'mechatkho l'evarim u'motzio k'dei l'hatzil et imo. You can actually commit an
abortion to save the mother. So there is a case where it's
actually מותר mutar and מצוה mitzvah for ישראל Yisrael, to do this,
okay, and it's forbidden for a non-Jew. For a non-Jew that would
still be murder. וכי האי גוונא בבני נח אסור כיון דאזהר להו
אעוברים. v'khei hai gavna b'vnei Noach assur keivan d'izhar lehu a'ubarim. If
for them it's murder, they wouldn't be able to choose the mother's
life over the fetus's life. This was a very big court case,
this exact issue.
Yeah, there's an... Okay, one minute. ויש לומר דהנא מבישראל מצוה כדי
להציל. v'yesh lomar d'hana m'b'Yisrael mitzvah k'dei l'hatzil. So first of all,
it's not we're not dealing with a difference between- we're dealing with
a difference between אסור assur and מותר, mutar, not אסור assur and
מצוה. mitzvah. So for a Jew it's a מצוה mitzvah to do
this and therefore it's not part of the discussion, okay? מצוה mitzvah
makes it sort of a shift of obligation. It's a קדושה kedusha
too, rather than a position of not of being forbidden, you have
a position of being commanded. But that's not like a more lenient
state of being. So we're not comparing it's a מצוה mitzvah case.
And then he says, ואפשר דאפילו בבני נח שרי. v'efshar d'afilu b'vnei
Noach sharei. It's possible that in that case it would be permitted
for non-Jews, okay, that it could be in the case of when
the mother's life is at stake. That even though it's considered רציחה,
retzichah, it is recognized as a as not yet a full life.
You're still חייב chayav for רציחה, retzichah, but it's still not yet
a full life. Okay, and therefore you would still have the same
permission and maybe even מצוה mitzvah to choose the mother's life over
the fetus's life. Right, you could still have a ranking even while
saying that even if you're at the bottom of the rank, it's
still רציחה retzichah doesn't mean that you don't have a ranking. Okay,
but what also becomes interesting here is a question I raised before,
which is like do בני נח bnei Noach, have a היתר heter
of, you know, the גמרא Gemara discussed before, it seemed like it
had the היתר heter of like of of killing a pursuer to
save the one being pursued, of רודף. rodef. Right, you remember the
גמרא Gemara discussed it before ויכול להצילו באחד מאיבריו. v'yakhol l'hatzilo b'echad
m'evarav. So it seemed like that idea does apply to בני נח,
bnei Noach right? And תוספות Tosafot is continuing with that. Meaning, yeah,
you could have said that they have an איסור רציחה issur retzichah
and they don't have a היתר heter to to kill a רודף.
rodef. But the assumption is that they do, both the earlier גמרא
Gemara and this תוספות. Tosafot. This תוספות Tosafot is just whether they
have this ranking. But there's other questions, like I said, do they
have an obligation of martyrdom? Are they supposed to, you know, or
maybe they're supposed to martyr themselves for everything? Like which way does
it go? Like it's not clear. All right, anyway, I don't want
to spend the whole thing on... Let's get back to the גמרא.
Gemara. Anyway, some fascinating issues in תוספות Tosafot that I didn't want
to pass up. Back to the
גמרא. Gemara. כל מצוה שנאמרה לבני נח ונשנית בסיני לזה ולזה נאמרה.
kol mitzvah she'ne'emrah l'vnei Noach v'nishniyata b'Sinai l'zeh u'l'zeh ne'emrah. Last two
lines. If it was said to בני נח bnei Noach, and repeated
at הר סיני, Har Sinai, it applies to both. So the גמרא
Gemara says one minute, והרי מילה שנאמרה לבני נח, v'harei milah she'ne'emrah
l'vnei Noach, מילה milah was given to בני נח, bnei Noach, דכתיב
ואתה את בריתי תשמור, dikhtiv v'atah et briti tishmor, so although it
was given to אברהם Avraham and not all of בני נח, bnei
Noach. that's considered בני נח. bnei Noach,
ונשנית בסיני וביום השמיני ימול בשר ערלתו. v'nishniyata b'Sinai u'vayom hashemini yimol
b'sar arlato. And that according to your logic, it should be said
to both, but that's not true. לישראל נאמרה ולא לבני נח, l'Yisrael
ne'emrah v'lo l'vnei Noach, and we know it applies to Jews and
not to non-Jews.
So the גמרא Gemara says ההוא למשרי שבת הוא דאתא ביום ואפילו
בשבת. hahu l'mishrei Shabbat hu d'ata bayom v'afilu b'Shabbat. That doesn't fit
in my category of repeated at הר סיני, Har Sinai, since the
only reason it says it over there in שמיני Shemini
and וביום השמיני ימול בשר ערלתו, u'vayom hashemini yimol b'sar arlato, the
only reason it says it is to tell you that you can
do it even on שבת, Shabbat, not to fundamentally command it. A
מצוה mitzvah doesn't need to fundamentally be repeated then at הר סיני
Har Sinai if it was given earlier. Right. Well, in order to
fit our principle that if it was repeated at הר סיני Har
Sinai it's said to both, we're going to say that sometimes repeat-
we're going to have a narrow definition of what repeated means. Okay,
repeated means that it was said again at הר סיני Har Sinai
for the sake of of the צווי tzivui alone. If it was
repeated in order to teach a certain הלכה, halakhah, you know, a
פרט, prat, a detail about it, that's not defined as repeated. They
say that about anything that's repeated to say. Basically, basically. It's a
way of keeping our structure and getting out of all the counter-evidence.
Okay, we're going to see a lot of things that were repeated
at הר סיני Har Sinai that that don't apply to בני נח,
Bnei Noach, and the answer's going to be it doesn't count as
being repeated because it was only to tell some detail. Okay, so
that's what it says. והרי פריה ורביה אמרת פרו ורבו שנאמרה לבני
נח. v'harei piryah v'rivyah amrat pru u'rvu she'ne'emrah l'vnei Noach. Basically, basically.
It's a way of keeping our structure and getting out of all
the counter-evidence. Okay, we're going to see a lot of things that
were repeated at הר סיני Har Sinai that don't apply to בני
נח, Bnei Noach. and the answer's going to be it doesn't count
as being repeated because it was only to tell some detail. Okay?
So that's what it says. אבל הרי פרו ורבו, Aval harei peru
u'revu, הא בא פרו ורבו שנאמר לבני נח, ha ba peru u'revu
she'ne'emar le'vnei Noach, נכתיב ואתם פרו ורבו, nich'tiv v'atem peru u'revu, ונשנה
בסיני, v'nishne b'Sinai, לכו אמרו להם שובו לכם לאהליכם. lechu amru lahem
shuvu lachem le'ohaleichem. That's a pretty funny example of נשנה בסיני, nishne
b'Sinai, right? When משה Moshe says go back to your wives, right?
That's לאהליכם le'ohaleichem is read, that means go back to being involved
in פרו ורבו peru u'revu and that's a מצוה mitzvah פרו ורבו.
peru u'revu. Or it might just mean that you're now allowed to
be with your wives because they weren't allowed, you know, leading up
to מתן תורה. Matan Torah. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara reads that as
the מצוה mitzvah פרו ורבו. peru u'revu. So the גמרא Gemara says,
לישראל נאמר ולא לבני נח, l'Yisrael ne'emar v'lo livnei Noach, and we
know that that's said to ישראל, Yisrael. not to בני נח. Bnei
Noach. So the גמרא Gemara says, ההוא וכל דבר שבמנין צריך מנין
אחר להתירו הוא דאתא. hahu v'chol davar she'be'minyan tzarich minyan acher le'hatiro
hu de'ata. No,
that, and there's a whole discussion in מסכת ביצה, Masechet Beitzah, you
know, God says במשוך היובל המה יעלו בהר, bimshoch ha'yovel heima ya'alu
va'har, right? That don't get to הר סיני Har Sinai until the,
you know, the divine presence departs and when you hear the שופר,
shofar, then you can go up, and the fact that you need
an explicit act to reverse the original edict, which was don't get
close to the mountain, teaches you that a something that is decreed
במנין, be'minyan, like, you know, by a בית דין, beit din, you
know, remains in effect until it is active, that decree is actively
retracted. Okay? And therefore, the same is true when it says אל
תגשו אל אשה, al tigshu el isha, you needed an explicit retraction,
and that's what it's teaching you that was retracting the prohibition, it
was not for the מצוה mitzvah פרו ורבו. peru u'revu. There's an
interesting discussion in רש"י Rashi and תוספות, Tosafot, what because this came
up in the Middle Ages. In the Middle Ages, the standard way
they, you know, made new legislation was they made various חרמים charamim
and edicts and so on. And let's say they did it with
a built-in sunset, for the next ten years. So, can the built-in
time be enough to say that it stops at the end of
that, or do you need to explicitly reverse it even when it
says a built-in time? Because here too, it was clear that it
was about הר סיני Har Sinai and nevertheless, it needed to be
explicitly reversed. Okay? So that's an interesting question within this parameter of
when you have to explicitly... It didn't say X number of days,
I understand. Okay, so that's why there was a debate. הוא דאתא.
Hu de'ata. Now, do they have no obligation at all for פרו
ורבו? peru u'revu? בני נח. Bnei Noach? Right. So now look at
this תוספות. Tosafot. So והא פריה ורביה. v'ha pirya v'rivya. תוספות Tosafot
says תימה מנלן דלא נאמר לבני נח? teima minalan d'lo ne'emar livnei
Noach? Why should I not think it applies to בני נח? Bnei
Noach. Why? Because it's not the שבע מצוות? sheva mitzvot? ואי משום
דלא חשיב לה בהדי שבע מצוות, הא למאן דאמר קום עשה לא
קא חשיב. v'i mishum d'lo chashiv lei bahadi sheva mitzvot, ha l'man
d'amar kum asei lo ka chashiv.
We're not mentioning obligations; we're mentioning things of prohibitions.
And it's very reasonable. It says פרו ורבו, peru u'revu, you know,
so central to the story of בראשית. Bereishit. You would think it
applies to בני נח. Bnei Noach שיש לומר דשב ואל תעשה נמי
הוא. she'yesh lomar d'shev v'al ta'aseh nami hu. No, it includes a
prohibition if you're מצווה metzuveh in פרו ורבו. peru u'revu. What prohibition
would it include? דמצווה אפריה ורביה מצווה שלא להשחית זרע. d'metzuveh apirya
v'rivya metzuveh she'lo le'hashchit zera. Prohibition not to be משחית זרע. mashchit
zera. Okay,
which is interesting. It gets to תוספות's Tosafot's whole approach towards השחתת
זרע hashchatat zera and masturbation. Is it fundamentally the problem of violation
of פרו ורבו peru u'revu and so on? Of course, the irony
is, is that according to a classic approach in חז"ל, Chazal, one
of the reasons for דור המבול, dor ha'mabul, כי השחית כל בשר,
ki hishchit kol basar, was because of השחתת זרע. hashchatat zera. And
according to this תוספות, Tosafot, he's saying בני נח Bnei Noach were
not commanded on פרו ורבו peru u'revu or השחתת זרע. hashchatat zera.
But I should say that some ראשונים Rishonim actually disagree. There are
some ראשונים Rishonim and there actually is a גמרא Gemara that makes
it sound like בני נח Bnei Noach are commanded on פרו ורבו.
peru u'revu. So this גמרא Gemara though assumes that they are not,
which is very strange reading the פסוקים. pesukim. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues.
So תוספות's Tosafot's answer as some ראשונים Rishonim understand this... So תוספות's
Tosafot's answer is we know that it doesn't apply to בני נח
Bnei Noach because otherwise it would have been in the list of
the שבע מצוות. sheva mitzvot. And what about the fact that it's
not a קום עשה? kum asei? Because it is a לא, lo,
because it is a prohibition. There's a prohibition aspect to it, so
had it applied to בני נח Bnei Noach it would have been
in the list. But then according... it means that even if you're
engaged in... but let's say you're with your wife or whatever, but
she's too old. So is that השחתת זרע hashchatat zera according?
No, the גמרא, Gemara, I mean that's a whole different discussion, but
the ראשונים Rishonim explicitly say השחתת זרע hashchatat zera is specifically about
like masturbation, it is not about normal... that every act of sex
has to have the potential of... what about when the woman is
pregnant? What about a million cases? Right. Anyway, it's a different discussion.
Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like this.
Yes, but according to this, it was because it wasn't repeated at
הר סיני, Har Sinai, the obligation shifted from בני נח Bnei Noach,
to ישראל. Yisrael. Go figure that one out.
I mean הר סיני Har Sinai come, meaning it could have been
always for בני נח, bnei Noach but once הר סיני Har Sinai
come and it wasn't repeated, the absence of repeating it somehow made
it shift to just בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. I don't get... I
can't figure that one out. All right, anyway, let's go on. Is
non-sex considered in masturbation? What? Or... you know, this is such a
completely different discussion. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay,
read my book. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אי הכי,
ei hachi, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, אי הכי כחדא
וחדא נמי נימא משום מילתא דאיתני? ei hachi k'chada v'chada nami neima
mishum milta d'itni?
So now it asks what Michael said, which is you're never going
to find something that was repeated. Every time something was repeated, you'll
tell me that wasn't really repeated because it was just to tell
you some detail. Look at that, Michael asked exactly that question.
הכי קאמר. hachi ka'amar. No, no. עשרה מהדר ומתני בהו למה
לי? asara m'hadar u'matni behu lama li? הכי קאמר, עשרה מהדר ומתני
בהו למה לי, ואין לנו אלא גיד הנשה גופא. hachi ka'amar, asara
m'hadar u'matni behu lama li, v'ein lanu ela gid ha'nasheh gufa. Meaning
it's sort of saying, yes, if there's just details, we'll say it's
just for the details. But if something is repeated just for its
prohibition, we're going to want to know why was it prohibited? And
if it was- so I don't really understand how the answer really,
you know, rejects the question. But it basically says if it's there's
just a detail, if it's about a detail, we'll say it's about
a detail. But if but but if it's it's prohibited,
but if you can't answer the question why was the prohibition repeated,
then I will say it was repeated for the sake of saying
that it applies to both. Okay, הכי קאמר: Hachi ka'amar: I don't
know how it answers the question of just a minute ago. הכי
קאמר: Hachi ka'amar: אזהרה, Azhara, the actual prohibition, מהדר ומתני בה למה
לי? me-hadar u-masni bah lama li? If I would want to know
why the prohibition was repeated. And if there was no good answer
why the prohibition was repeated, then it would be to say that
it applies to both. And the only case I have that is
אמרו לו ואין לנו אלא גיד הנשה בלבד ואליבא דרבי יהודה. Amru
lo ve-ain lanu ella gid hanasheh bilvad va-aliba de-Rabbi Yehuda. Only גיד
הנשה gid hanasheh according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, who says that
the פסוק pasuk of על כן לא יאכלו בני ישראל את גיד
הנשה al ken lo yochelo bnei Yisrael et gid hanasheh was said
at that time. So originally it was said to בני נח bnei
Noach and that wasn't repeated, excuse me, and that wasn't repeated. And
that's the one case of something that wasn't repeated and applies to
בני ישראל. bnei Yisrael. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says: הני נמי
לא יתנו? Hani nami lo yasnu? So הני, hani, these... wait, hold
on, I'm sorry, I've got to read to myself how to read
this. Oh, so the גמרא Gemara
says, right: הני נמי לא יתנו? Hani nami lo yasnu? So these
of מילה ופרו ורבו... mila u-pru u-rvu... Oh, now I see. So
now the גמרא's Gemara question is... I'm sorry, I got confused for
a second. Okay. So now we've said, wait a minute, but you
said the only thing that wasn't repeated was גיד הנשה. gid hanasheh.
But we've also just said that פרו ורבו pru u-rvu and ברית
מילה, bris mila, even though they were repeated, you said effectively they
weren't repeated. And that's why it applies only to
ישראל. So why does this previous statement say it's only גיד הנשה
gid hanasheh that wasn't repeated? According to the way you just answered
my previous question, פרו ורבו pru u-rvu and ברית מילה bris mila
were also not repeated. So
the גמרא Gemara says: הני נמי לא יתנו? Hani nami lo yasnu?
So what do you mean? According to you, פרו ורבו pru u-rvu
and ברית מילה bris mila also weren't
repeated. No: הני יתנו לשום מילתא בעלמא. Hani yasnu le-shum milta be-alma.
They were repeated to teach me something. When I said there was
nothing that wasn't repeated, I mean nothing that wasn't repeated at all.
Okay? So because it was
repeated... because it was actually repeated, ברית מילה bris mila and פרו
ורבו, pru u-rvu, it's not in the list of things that were
never repeated. But because it was repeated to teach me something, it's
not in the list of things that were repeated in order to,
you know, that would say that it applies to both. Okay, איבעית
אימא, I-ba'is eima, if I want, I can give you another answer.
מילה, Mila, a more satisfying answer by ברית מילה. bris mila. מילה
מעיקרא לאברהם הוא דקא מזהר ליה רחמנא. Mila me-ikara le-Avraham hu de-ka
mazhar lei Rachmana. מילה Mila was never said to בני נח bnei
Noach, that it should fall in this category of being repeated and
applying to both. מילה Mila from the outset applied only to a
subset of בני נח, bnei Noach, it only applied to
אברהם. Avraham. Okay? ואתה את בריתי תשמור אתה וזרעך אחריך לדורותם. Ve-ata
et brisi tishmor ata ve-zar'acha acharecha le-dorotam. אתה וזרעך, Ata ve-zar'acha, you
and your seed, yes; אינשי אחריני לא, Inshi achareini lo, nobody else.
Okay, so ברית מילה bris mila was never said to all of
בני נח, bnei Noach. so it's not in this category. אלא מעתה,
Ella me-ata, says the גמרא, Gemara, בני ישמעאל ליחייבו? bnei Yishmael le-chayivu?
Okay, so if that's true, if we don't focus on the fact
that it was repeated at Har Sinai, we're actually being guided by
the
מצוה mitzvah of מילה mila as given to אברהם, Avraham, because according
to this answer, we're saying the fact that it was repeated at
Sinai doesn't take it away from בני נח. bnei Noach Yes, it
was to בני נח bnei Noach and at Sinai, but בני נח
benei Noach. ultimately means אברהם. Avraham. So it means that we're basically
following... I mean, here's an interesting question to ask: when we do
a ברית מילה, bris mila, which מצוה mitzvah are we being מקיים?
mekayeim? The מצוה mitzvah that God said to אברהם, Avraham, or the
מצוה mitzvah that appears where it says וביום השמיני ימול בשר ערלתו?
U-vayom ha-shmini yimol bsar orlato? So that's essentially what this גמרא Gemara
is saying. But the גמרא Gemara is saying: oh, but if you're
making that מצוה mitzvah a lasting מצוה, mitzvah, then it should apply
to בני ישמעאל bnei Yishmael as well, because it's אברהם's Avraham seed.
So the גמרא Gemara says: כי ביצחק יקרא לך זרע. Ki ve-Yitzchak
yikare lcha zara. No, only your seed, it says וזרעך אחריך, ve-zar'acha
acharecha, so וזרעך אחריך ve-zar'acha acharecha is יצחק, Yitzchak, not ישמעאל. Yishmael.
Technically, biologically he's your seed, but he's not called your seed. So
the גמרא Gemara says: בני עשו ליחייבו? bnei Esav le-chayivu? Okay, how
about בני
עשו? bnei Esav? ביצחק ולא כל יצחק. Be-Yitzchak ve-lo kol Yitzchak. Within
יצחק, Yitzchak, not all of יצחק. Yitzchak. Okay, so the official זרע,
zera, the family of אברהם, Avraham, right? Not the biological seed, but
the family is אברהם יצחק ויעקב. Avraham Yitzchak ve-Yaakov. And that's where...
that's why we are doing ברית מילה bris mila based on that
ציווי. tzivui. Even though, yes, it was repeated, but fine, it was
repeated, it applies
before and after Sinai, but the before is limited to אברהם Avraham
and his family. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: מתקיף
לה רב אושעיא. Mas kif lah Rav Oshaya. Part of אברהם, Avraham,
right, exactly. מתקיף לה... Mas kif lah... Part of אברהם *Avraham*, right,
exactly. מתקיף ליה *maskivle* says what I said, family. מתקיף ליה רב
הושעיא *maskivle Rav Oshaya*, so רב הושעיא *Rav Oshaya* says, אלא מעתה
ela me'ata, בני קטורה לא ליחייבו *elo mi'ata b'nei keturah lo lichayevu*?
So according to this, why did אברהם *Avraham* give a ברית מילה
*Brit Milah* to the children of קטורה *Keturah*? Okay, the way רש"י
*Rashi* says this, it does not mean בני קטורה *b'nei keturah* as
a nation, as a future family. It means the actual children of
קטורה *Keturah*. Why how does it assume that he did? Okay, and
would you tell me not because it's only יצחק *Yitzchak* and not
other kids? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אמר Amar רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi ברבי אבין ותימרי רבי יוסי Yose ברבי חנינא *Amar Rabbi
Yose b'Rabbi Avin ve'temari Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina* את בריתי הפר *Es
Briti Hafar* means that right now אברהם *Avraham* for you yourself you've
got to give a ברית מילה *Brit Milah* to all your kids.
Okay, but in terms of the as an eternal מצוה *mitzvah*, that's
only יצחק *Yitzchak* and then the Abrahamic family narrowly defined. Fine. אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב *Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav*. So that's interesting
because that's the question of is our doing a ברית מילה *Brit
Milah* a fulfillment of the ציווי *tzivuy* to אברהם *Avraham* or the
ציווי *tzivuy* from later on where it says ביום השמיני ימול *bayom
hashmini yimol*. Okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב *Amar Rav Yehuda Amar
Rav* אדם הראשון Adam HaRishon *Adam HaRishon* לא הותר לו בשר לאכילה
*lo hutar lo basar le'achila*. We finally move beyond this whether it
was said and repeated or not repeated, which is always so confusing
and there's no good logic to it. Anyway, so now a different
point since we're talking about אדם Adam הראשון *Adam HaRishon*. אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב *Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav* אדם Adam הראשון *Adam
HaRishon* לא הותר לו בשר לאכילה *lo hutar lo basar le'achila*.
He was not permitted to eat meat. Okay, it wasn't just אבר
מן man, החי *ever min hachai*, he wasn't permitted to eat meat,
דכתיב dechtiv, *dechsiv* לכם יהיה לאכלה לכל חית הארץ *lachem yihiyeh le'achla
lechol chayat ha'aretz*. Okay, for you this כל ירק עשב *kol yerek
esev*, all the herbs, all the vegetation will be to eat, and
for all the animals, so they will eat the vegetation, but ולא
חית הארץ לכם *velo chayat ha'aretz lachem*, but you don't get to
eat the animals. Okay, you and the animals get to eat the
vegetation. Okay, again to remind you, רש"י *Rashi* says you only need
to prohibit אבר מן החי *ever min hachai* because this wasn't really
a prohibition the way רש"י *Rashi* reads this to eat meat, it
was a prohibition to kill an animal to eat meat. Okay, and
anyway this is a separate prohibition not to eat meat even if
it died on its own. No, no. רש"י *Rashi* interprets what this
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* means is that he can't kill an animal to
eat meat, but he was allowed to eat meat if an animal
died on its own, and that's why there had to be a
prohibition of אבר מן החי *ever min hachai*. Okay, that's what רש"י
*Rashi* says, but that's not פשט *pshat*. פשט *pshat* of this גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is that he wasn't permitted to eat meat at all.
Okay, maybe you leave the אבר מן החי *ever min hachai* ציווי
*tzivuy* to נח *Noach*. We heard an earlier opinion, right, that it
wasn't אדם Adam *Adam* that was commanded in אבר מן החי *ever
min hachai*, it was נח *Noach*. So then it's possible to read
this like the פשט *pshat* that he wasn't permitted to eat meat
at all. וכשבאו בני נח benei Noach. *uchesheba'u bnei Noach* בני נח
benei Noach *bnei Noach* came, הותר להם *hutar lahem*, it was permitted,
שנאמר *shenemar* כירק עשב נתתי לכם את הכל *keyerek esev natati lachem
et hakol*. Like the grass, I've permitted everything, even animals to you.
יכול לא יהיה אבר מן החי נוהג בו *yachol lo yihiyeh ever
min hachai noheg bo*, maybe for all is permitted even אבר מן
החי *ever min hachai* is permitted to בני נח benei Noach *bnei
Noach*, תלמוד לומר *talmud lomar* אך בשר בנפשו דמו לא תאכלו *ach
basar benafsho damo lo socheilu*. יכול אף לשרצים *yachol af lishratzim*, maybe
even for rodents this prohibition of אבר מן החי *ever min hachai*
applies, תלמוד לומר *talmud lomar* אך *ach*. ומאי תלמודא *u'mai talmuda*, where
do you get it from? אמר רבי הונא *Amar Rabbi Huna* דמו
*damo*,
its blood. מי שדמו חלוק מבשרו *mi shedamo choluk mibesaro*, some animal
that the blood is seen as distinct from the flesh, יצאו שרצים
שאין דמם חלוק מבשרם *yatzeu sheratzim she'ein damam choluk mibesaram* as opposed
to rodents where it's not seen as distinct from their flesh. I
don't know why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* thinks that. Anyway, that's why
אבר מן החי *ever min hachai* does not apply to שרצים *sheratzim*.
We've seen most of these ideas before. מיתיבי Meitivei *Meisvei* they ask
on this, ורדו בדגת הים *uredu bidgat hayam*,
so you should have mastery over the fish of the sea. מאי
לאו לאכילה *mai lav le'achila*, if you have mastery, presumably it means
you're allowed to eat them? לא למלאכה *lo limlacha*, no, you can
use the fish to do work for you. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says ודגים בני מלאכה נינהו *vedagim bnei melacha ninhu*, can you
somehow do work with fish? אין In *In*, yes, כי הא דרבה
דבר רחבא *ki de'Rabba debar Rechava* רחבא *Rechava* asked, הנהיג בעז ושיבוטא
מאי *hinhig be'iza veshivuta mai*.
Let's say you had a goat and a שיבוטא *shivuta*, a certain
type of a fish, pulling your plow, would that be an איסור
*issur* of כלאים kilayim. *kilayim*? Okay, or כלאים kilayim, *kilayim* only with
land animals? Anyway, somehow, I mean, look, if it's not a whale,
you could get a whale to do some work, a porpoise maybe,
I don't know about a normal fish. Anyway, תא שמע Ta shema
*ta shema*, come and hear, ובעוף השמים *uve'of
hashamayim*, like you have mastery over the birds of the heaven. מאי
לאו לאכילה *mai lav le'achila*, does it not mean that you were
allowed to eat it? לא למלאכה *lo limlacha*, to get them to
do work. ועופות בני מלאכה נינהו *ve'ofos bnei melacha ninhu*, can they
do work? I don't know, you could have like homing pigeons, you
can do work with birds, get roosters to lay eggs, excuse me,
hens to lay eggs. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אין In
*In*, yes, כי הא דרבה בר רב הונא *ki de'Rabba bar Rav
Huna* דש באווזים ותרנגולים *dash be'avazim vetarnigolim*, so
if somebody threshed, used ducks or roosters to thresh their food, ורבי
יוסי Yose, ברבי יהודה *ve'Rabbi Yosi bar Rabbi Yehuda* מאי *mai*, what
would be the story? Now what, you think that this is again
a כלאים kilayim *kilayim* question, but it's not. The רבי יוסי Yose
ברבי יהודה *Rabbi Yosi bar Rabbi Yehuda* says that an animal, a
human worker or an animal to have the right to eat when
they're working, has to use both their arms, their legs and their
arms. Okay, so an animal uses all fours as it's threshing, a
human would have to use both his legs and his arms when
he's working. So it says, well let's say it's an animal that
didn't have arms, that just had legs. Okay, would it be allowed
to eat, would you be allowed to muzzle it while it was
working? Anyway, look, you could go ahead and you could do that.
I don't know why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* just didn't say you
can make them work to make them lay eggs. I mean, presumably...
Probably he didn't have to be a vegan, he could have been
a vegetarian, he could have right he could have he could have
used their eggs. Okay, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
רבי יוסי
so the גמרא Gemara, says מה? mah? תא שמע come and hear:
בכל חיה הרומשת על הארץ B'chol chaya haromeset al ha'aretz
mastery over all of the wild animals. So what type of use
do you have for wild animals? I mean, domesticated animals is one
thing. So the גמרא Gemara says ההוא לאתויי נחש הוא דאתא Hahu
l'atuyei nachash hu d'ata to include the serpent. דתניא D'tanya we taught
in a ברייתא Baraita רבי שמעון בן מנסיא Rabbi Shimon ben Menasya
אומר omer חבל על שמש גדול שאבד מן העולם Chaval al shamash
gadol she'avad min ha'olam woe
to the fact that we lost such a great servant to the
world. שאילמלא נתקלקל נחש She'ilmalei nitkalkel nachash
if it had not been for the sin of the נחש, nachash,
you know, and the sin of אדם whatever, we would have, I
mean he had legs before he sinned. So he could have been,
you know, do you imagine him as like a big centipede or
do you imagine him still as the נחש nachash standing upright on
his legs? So you know, before the sin though he would have
been much more useful and he would have been subservient to אדם
and we could have used this great servant the נחש. nachash. What
would we have done? כל אחד ואחד מישראל Kol echad v'echad mi'Yisrael
every Jew—I don't know why the נחשים nechashim would have only served
Jews—anyway היו מזדמנים לו שני נחשים טובים hayu mizdamnim lo shnei nechashim
tovim there would have had two נחשים nechashim to attend to them.
אחד משגרו לצפון ואחד משגרו לדרום Echad meshagro l'tzafon v'echad meshagro l'darom
one he would send to the north and one he would send
to the south ומביאין לו סנדלבונין u'mevi'in lo sandalbunin some type of
precious jewel טובים ואבנים טובות ומרגליות tovim v'avanim tovot u'margaliyot
would bring them all precious jewels. ולא עוד V'lo od and not
only that אלא שמתשילין רצועה תחת זנבו ela she'matshilin ritzua tachat zanavo
you would put a like a string under or a strap under
its tail ומוציא בה עפר לגינתו ולחורבתו u'motzi ba afar l'ginato u'l'chorvato
and then as it would be walking it would be turning the
dirt upside down or whatever
and therefore you would be able to use the dirt that it
had overturned to, you know, to plant in your garden. Okay, so
אוי נאבעך oy nebukh some people, you know, some want to say
that this is like a, this is what, like a, you know,
sort of a little bit of a humor. Like they would have
gotten the most precious jewels and not only that they even would
have gotten us dung for our gardens. Anyway, okay. So anyway, anyway
fine. So okay, so even though obviously a way to read the
opening part of בראשית Bereshit is אדם has mastery, he can eat
them, but the גמרא Gemara is saying no he can't eat them,
he could only eat vegetation and this mastery is for other purposes.
Okay, מיתיבי I ask you on this: היה רבי יהודה בן תימא
אומר Haya Rabbi Yehuda ben Teima omer אדם הראשון מיסב בגן עדן
היה Adam HaRishon meiseiv b'Gan Eden haya אדם הראשון was like reclining
in גן עדן Gan Eden eating a banquet ומלאכי השרת צולים לו
בשר u'malachei haShareit tzolim lo basar and the heavenly angels would be
there to barbecue roasting for him some meat ומסננין לו יין u'mesannin
lo yayin and cooling, you know, what do you, and like filtering
the wine
for him. הציץ בו נחש Heitzitz bo Nachash so the serpent peered
at him saw all of the privilege that he had וראה בכבודו
ונתקנא בו v'ra b'kvodo v'nitkana bo and was jealous and that's why
the נחש Nachash seduced חוה. Chava. Okay, so anyway you see though
he was eating meat, he was at a barbecue. So the גמרא
Gemara says no התם בבשר היורד מן השמיים hatam b'vasar hayored min
hashamayim so that was not actual animals that had lived, that was
a special meat that was sent from heaven. Okay, it started off
as meat, didn't start off as a live animal. So the גמרא
Gemara says מי איכא בשר היורד מן השמיים? Mi ika basar hayored
min hashamayim? Is there such a thing? אין yes. Because of course
when you hear that יורד מן השמיים בשר yored min hashamayim basar
whatever, you think about like the שליו slav and the מן, right?
Anyway yes, but the גמרא's Gemara point is that the animal was
never alive I think. אין yes כי הא דרבי שמעון בן חלפתא
ki ha d'Rabbi Shimon ben Chalafta the story of רבי שמעון בן
חלפתא. Rabbi Shimon ben Chalafta. הוה קאזיל באורחא Hava ka'azil b'orchah he
was going on the way פגעו בו הנך אריוותא pagu bo hanach
aryavata so certain lions encountered him דהוו קא נהמי באפיה d'havu ka
nahamei b'apeih they were roaring and they were going to eat him.
אמר so he said הכפירים שואגים לטרף hakefirim sho'agim lateref so the,
you know, the lions whelps cry out to consume and, you know,
basically and said like, you know, it was a type of a
תפילה. tefillah. And what happened? נחיתו ליה תרתי אטמתא Nichasu lei tarti
atmata it came down from heaven two big sides of beef. חדא
אכלוהא Chada achluha one they ate and they walked away and didn't
hurt him וחדא שבקוהא v'chada shavkuha they left it. אייתי ואתא Aiti
v'ata l'vei midrasha, he took this whole big side of beef and
he brought it into the בית מדרש. Beit Medrash. בעא להו Ba'ei
lehu he said דבר טמא הוא זה או דבר טהור? Davar tamei
hu zeh o davar tahor? Is it kosher or טרייף? treif? אמרו
ליה Amru lei they said to him אין דבר טמא יורד מן
השמיים Ein davar tamei yored min hashamayim if it came from heaven
it can't be טרייף. treif. בעי מיניה רבי זירא מרבי אבהו Ba'ei
minei Rabbi Zeira me'Rabbi Abahu רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira asked רבי אבהו:
Rabbi Abahu: how far would you say that there can't be anything
טרייף treif that comes from heaven? ירדה לו דמות חמור מהו? Yarda
lo d'mut chamor mahu? Let's say if a donkey, something looking like
a donkey descended from heaven, would it be kosher? אמר ליה Amar
lei ירוד נאעל Yarud na'al sort of like howling, what do they
call, how do they translate that? Howling something type of animal, howling
serpent or something. So הא אמרי ליה אין דבר טמא יורד מן
השמיים Ha amri lei ein davar tamei yored min hashamayim I don't
understand you asking such a stupid question. Nothing טרייף treif ever comes
from heaven so even if it looks like a donkey it's kosher.
Okay, so this was a very humorous little diversion here. What? Vegan
pork. Ah, so it's interesting that You say that because there's a
whole discussion now they're making in the laboratory, they're using like the
cells of animals to try and essentially to be able to make
laboratory grown meat without an you know with it's totally in the
laboratory. It starts by a cell and then but you know and
then they duplicate it and so on. So the question is is
it going to be kosher or not? So the real question is
to what degree... yeah, then oh, I don't think I don't think
it is well, it's interesting whether vegans will choose to eat it
but I think that the basic purpose is just because of the
like the environmental costs and the otherwise costs of raising meat or
something. Well, not now, not now, but if they perfect the process,
you know? Anyway, so that's going to be the whole question. So
the basic question is, you know, how much does it retain its
identity as טריף traif when it gets down to like a cellular
level and then how much does the thing that come out of
it is that considered טריף traif and so on? But some some
פוסקים poskim when they talk about the issue start with this story
about like miraculous meat, you know? You could have donkey meat that's
not from a real donkey. Okay? Anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues. They could do it with a kosher cell. What? They could
do it with a kosher cell. Yes, yes, but it wouldn't have
been שחט, shechted, you know? So that's a different issue. Yes. We
could try to ask them, can you start with a cell from
a שחט shechted animal? Make it make it better for the Jews.
I am sure that once they get this perfected, there's somebody that's
going to come out with a brand that's going to have started
from a kosher meat. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: רבי שמעון אומר אף על כישוף. Rabbi Shimon omer af al
kishuf. Finally we're moving back to well we go back to we're
going back to some of the earlier discussions of the שבע מצוות
sheva mitzvot and those that had a wider range. רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says it even includes witchcraft. And one of the proofs of
this was the way in which the תורה Torah sort of says
that because of all these תועבות, to'evot, you know, God is driving
the nations out and with listing all of the acts of witchcraft.
מאי טעמא דרבי שמעון? Mai ta'ama deRabbi Shimon? What's the reason? דכתיב,
dechitiv, but רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon maybe didn't wouldn't say that. מכשפה
לא תחיה. mechashafa lo techaye. Do not allow a suffer a witch
to live, as King James translates it. וכתיב, vechtiv, and it says
כל שכב עם בהמה מות יומת, kol shocheiv im behema mot yumat,
the end of the פסוק pasuk is about an act of bestiality.
כל שישנו בכלל כל שכב עם בהמה ישנו בכלל מכשפה לא תחיה,
kol sheyeshno biklal kol shocheiv im behema yeshno biklal mechashafa lo techaye,
anybody that's included in the prohibition of sleeping with an animal is
also included in the prohibition of witchcraft and that would include בני
נח. benei Noach, רבי אליעזר אומר אף על כלאים. Rabbi Eliezer omer
af al kilayim. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says even כלאים. kilayim מנא
הני מילי? minan hani mili? Where do we know this from? אמר
שמואל ואמר קרא: amar Shmuel ve'amar kra: את חקתי תשמרו. et chukotai
tishmoru. Observe my edicts. חקים שחקקתי לך כבר. chukim shechakakti lecha kevar.
Since it doesn't say תשמרו חקתי tishmoru chukotai but את חקתי תשמרו,
et chukotai tishmoru, things that are already my edicts you should observe.
And then it goes ahead and speaks about בהמתך לא תרביע כלאים.
behemtcha lo tarbi'a kilayim. Don't do crossbreeding with your animal. So that
means that this is an edict that preexisted Me commanding it to
you right now, you בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael right now. It was
an edict that already existed from the time of בני נח. benei
Noach, Okay, בהמתך לא תרביע כלאים ושדך לא תזרע כלאים. behemtcha lo
tarbi'a kilayim vesadcha lo tizra kilayim. מה בהמתך בהרכבה אף שדך בהרכבה.
ma behemtcha beharkava af sadcha beharkava. So the same way your animals
means by crossbreeding, so when we say your field don't plant כלאים,
kilayim, we don't mean don't plant mixed seeds, but it has to
be a similar idea of actually crossbreeding the two things themselves, not
allowing them to grow together, which would be the case of two
seeds. So it would actually be an issue of grafting. So for
בני נח benei Noach? only grafting is prohibited. מה בהמתך בין בארץ
בין בחוץ לארץ, ma behemtcha bein ba'aretz bein bechutz la'aretz, and the
same way your animal the prohibition of כלאים kilayim. applies even in
בחוץ לארץ, bechutz la'aretz, because why should it be limited to the
land of Israel? אף שדך בין בארץ בין בחוץ לארץ. af sadcha
bein ba'aretz bein bechutz la'aretz. So for בני נח b'nei Noach the
prohibition of כלאים applies equally in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and in
בחוץ לארץ bechutz la'aretz as for בני נח, Bnei Noach you know,
obviously for them the ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael status isn't meaningful, it
applies equally. Now how about for בני ישראל? Bnei Yisrael? For בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael כלאים, if I'm remembering correctly, only applies in בחוץ
לארץ, bechutz la'aretz, I think only מדרבנן miderabbanan if I'm remembering correctly,
maybe מדברי סופרים. midivrei soferim. But anyway, for בני נח, it's not
clearly it's not limited to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay, אלא מעתה,
so that's if you're going to learn the דרשה drasha that way
says the גמרא, Gemara ושמרתם את חקתי ואת משפטי, ushmartem et chukotai
ve'et mishpatai, why don't you say observe my חקות chukot and my
משפטים? mishpatim? Why don't you say חקותי chukotai means חקים שחקקתי לך
כבר? chukim shechakakti lecha kevar? So maybe it means and then it
lists you know many other מצוות, mitzvot, why don't I say that
these also applied to בני נח? So the גמרא Gemara says no.
ושמרתם את חקתי דהשתא, ushmartem et chukotai dehashta, there it says, I'm
sorry, I skipped a line. ואת משפטי חקים ש- ve'et mishpatai chukim
she- ah, השתא, dehashta, there ושמרתם את חקתי דהשתא. ushmartem et chukotai
dehashta. Since the word חקותי chukotai comes after the command ושמרתם, ushmartem,
it means the edicts I'm commanding you now. הכא, hacha, את חקתי,
et chukotai, the word חק chuk comes first, תשמרו, tishmoru, חקים דמעיקרא,
chukim demikara, the חקים chukim that already exist תשמרו tishmoru you have
to observe. Okay, so that's where you get the idea of כלאים.
אמר רבי יהושע בן קרחה. amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha. Now we
get back to the major point of the משנה Mishna which you
might remember which was about blaspheming. We only got to the שבע
מצוות בני נח sheva mitzvos b'nei Noach because we discussed that that
was included, the בני נח were included in that prohibition. Okay, but
now we return to the idea of blaspheming, and רבי יהושע בן
קרחה Rebbi Yehoshua ben Korcha describes that the עדים edim the whole
פי התם pi hatam would say what did he say, יכה יוסי
את יוסי Yake Yose es Yosi until it came the time that
they actually would have to make the final testimony where they would
say God's name explicitly. So the גמרא gemara. says like this: אמר
רב אחא בר יעקב, Amar Rav Achai bar Yaakov, אינו חייב עד
שיברך שם בין ארבע אותיות. eino chayav ad sheyivarech shem bein arba
osios. Okay, so we discussed before that it has to be using
God's name to curse God's name, and here it's saying, and if
you remember, there's a whole point about whether it had to be
the שם המפורש shem hamiforash or even a כינוי, kinuy, right? You
might remember because the פסוקים psukim talk about נוקב שם השם. nokeiv
shem Hashem. So he's saying it has to be the שם המפורש.
shem hamiforash. You have to use the four-letter name of God, the
יוד-קא-ואו-קא. Yud-Kei-Vav-Kei. Okay, לאפוקי l'afukei between two letters. If it was only
the two letters יוד-קא Yud-Kei or א-ל El or something like that,
that would be a כינוי kinuy and that you would not be,
you might be חייב כרת chayav kares but you wouldn't get the
death penalty. Okay, דלא, d'lo, that would not be included. פשיטא, Pshuta,
of course. יכה יוסי את יוסי תנן. Yake Yose es Yosi t'nan.
When the משנה Mishna speaks about the example, it gives the example
of יוסי את יוסי Yose es Yosi and the word יוסי presumably
was chosen because it was four letters, you got a יוד yud
and a ואו vav and so on. So the גמרא says no,
מהו דתימא מילתא בעלמא הוא דנקט. mahu d'teima miltsa b'alma hu d'nakat.
No, just because it used the word יוסי, maybe that's just a
random word that it used, you know, that doesn't, is not coming
to signify it needs to be God's four-letter name, קא משמע לן
ka mashma lan that it does have to be God's four-letter name.
איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some say, אמר רב אחא בר יעקב, Amar
Rav Achai bar Yaakov, שמע מינה שם בין ארבע אותיות נמי שם
הוא. shma mina shem bein arba osios nami shem hu. Ah, we
see from יוסי את יוסי Yose es Yosi that if you use
God's four-letter name as opposed to God's expanded name, I don't know
if you knew that God had an expanded name. So רש״י Rashi
says the expanded name of 42 letters, okay, that that, so it's
not the full שם המפורש shem hamiforash which is 42 letters, it's
even the שם המפורש shem hamiforash of four letters. And we know
it because it says יוסי את יוסי. Yose es Yosi. Okay, שמע
מינה שם בין ארבע אותיות נמי שם הוא. shma mina shem bein
arba osios nami shem hu. פשיטא, Pshuta, obviously, יכה יוסי את יוסי
תנן. Yake Yose es Yosi t'nan. No, מהו דתימא עד דאיכא שם
רבא. mahu d'teima ad d'ika shem raba. No, you need God's expanded
name ומילתא בעלמא הוא דנקט umiltsa b'alma hu d'nakat and using the
example of יוסי was just a convenient way like we just took
any name, it's not there to signify God's four-letter name, קא משמע
לן ka mashma lan that it does signify that. It needs to
be God's four-letter name and even if it's only God's four-letter name,
presumably certainly if it's God's 42-letter name. Okay. ניגמר הדין. Nigmar hadin.
Now, once they finish all the דרשות, drashos, they made everybody leave
the court and then they said tell us exactly what you heard
and they said it with God's name and everybody stood up and
did קריעה. kriya. עומדים. Omdim. Now where do we know that they
have to stand up, מנלן, minalan, where do you get that from?
אמר רב יהודה בר אמי, Amar Rav Yehuda bar Ami, דאמר קרא,
d'amar kra, the verse says: ואהוד בא אליו והוא יושב בעליית המקרה.
V'ehu ba elav v'hu yoshev b'aliyas hamikra. So אהוד Ehud came to
him, this was, who was this, this was a foreign king, אגלון,
Eglon, מלך מואב. Melech Moav. Okay, אשר לו לבדו ויאמר אהוד דבר
אלהים לי אליך. asher lo l'vado vayomer Ehud dvar Elohim li eilecha.
I have a word, a message from God for you, king. ויקם
מעל הכסא. Vayakom me'al hakisay. And he arose from his throne to
hear what God had to say. והלא דברים קל וחומר. V'halo d'varim
kal vachomer. Make a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה אגלון מלך מואב
שהוא נכרי, Umah Eglon Melech Moav shehu nochri, he was a non-Jew
ולא ידע אלא בכינוי, v'lo yada ela b'kinuy, and he only knew
God, you know, כינוי kinuy name, אלהים, Elohim, he didn't even know
יוד-קא-ואו-קא. Yud-Kei-Vav-Kei. And nevertheless, עמד, amad, he stood up when God's name
was being articulated, you know, enunciated. So ישראל ושם המפורש על אחת
כמה וכמה. Yisrael v'shem hamiforash al achas kama v'kama. If it was
a Jew and you're saying God's explicit name, how much more so
you have to stand. Now this is interesting because right in the
משנה Mishna you got the sense the reason they stood and did
קריעה kriya was because God was being cursed. But this makes it
sound like they just have to stand for the sake that God's
name was being articulated. But is that really true anytime somebody says
the word א-ל El or אלהים Elohim or even אלף-דלת-נון-יוד Alef-Daled-Nun-Yud somebody's
got to stand? You know, maybe יוד-קא-ואו-קא. Yud-Kei-Vav-Kei. But based on the
fact that it's learning it from this פסוק pasuk of אלהים, Elohim,
for logical thing to derive would be anytime God's name is said
you would have to stand, which is certainly what we don't say
that. Anyway, so it's interesting the גמרא takes it out of the
context of doing קריעה. kriya. Now the גמרא continues. Okay. קורע מנלן.
Koreia minalan. How do you know you have to do קריעה kriya
when you hear God's name being blasphemed? דכתיב ויבא אליקים בן חלקיהו
ושבנא הסופר ויואח בן אסף המזכיר אל חזקיהו. d'chsiv Vayavo Elyakim ben
Chilkiyahu v'Shevna hasofer v'Yoach ben Asaf hamazkir el Chizkiyahu. These three whatever
officers came to חזקיהו, Chizkiyahu, קרועי בגדים, kru'ei begadim, of rent garments
because they heard this person רבשקה, Ravshakeh, you know, cursing out God's
name, you know, who was sent by the king of אשור. Ashur.
ויגידו לו את דברי רבשקה. Vayagidu lo es divrei Ravshakeh. So you
see that they rent their garments. Okay. ולא מאחים. V'lo ma'achim. Now
after their garments are rent, they are not sewn up, they remain
that way. This is also when a person does קריעה kriya over
a parent, right? And this whole discussion right about parents and... being
equal to שכינה Shekhinah and so on. So the only other type
of קריעה keriah that's not sewn up is קריעה keriah over parent.
מנלן? Minalan? Where does this come from? אמר רבי אבהו, Amar Rabbi
Abahu, אתיא קריעה קריעה. atya keriah keriah. You make a גזרה שוה.
gezeirah shavah. כתיב הכא Ketiv hacha קרועי בגדיהם, keruei vigdeihem, which was
done because of God's name being blasphemed, וכתיב התם uchetiv hatam ואלישע
רואה ואליהו עולה בסערה השמימה, veElisha roeh veEliyahu oleh besa'arah hashamaymah, אלישע
Elisha saw when אליהו Eliyahu is going up in the fiery chariot,
והוא מצעק vehu mitzaek אבי אבי רכב ישראל ופרשיו, avi avi rechev
Yisrael ufarashav, father, father, chariot of Israel and its horsemen. ולא ראהו
עוד, Velo ra'ahu od, he no longer saw אליהו Eliyahu after that,
ויחזק בבגדיו, vayachazek bivgadov, he took hold of his garments, ויקרעם לשנים
קרעים, vayikra'em lishnayim kera'im, and he rent them into two tears. So
the גמרא says, ממשמע שנאמר mimmashma shene'emar ויקרעם לשנים, vayikra'em lishnayim, he
rent them into two, איני יודע שהם קרעים, eini yodeia shehem kera'im,
of course he made tears. מה תלמוד לומר mah talmud lomar קרעים?
kera'im? What does it say tears? מלמד שהם קרועים לעולם, melamed shehem
keruim le'olam, they remain that way forever. And again, there it's sort
of seeing אליהו Eliyahu in a father type of a figure, so
it's קריעה keriah on a father where also you don't mend it,
and here too, and based on גזרה שוה, gezeirah shavah, you don't
mend it for the case of blasphemy. הרואה ערי יהודה בחורבנם, Haroeh
arei Yehudah bechurbanam, yeah, I think that that could be mended, I'm
pretty... yeah, I think so. ירושלים בחורבנה, Yerushalayim bechurbanah, do you think?
I mean, maybe, it's an... right, it's interesting, yeah, could be. תנו
רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, yes? No, no, no, the קריעה keriah is only
hearing God's name being blasphemed. Standing was associated with just hearing God's
name, but the קריעה keriah is hearing God's name being blasphemed, which
is what the story was with רבשקה. Ravshakeh. רבשקה Ravshakeh was... the
פסוקים pesukim say that he was מחרף אלהי ישראל, meharef Elohei Yisrael,
like he was מחרף meharef God. So but when you hear God's
name being blasphemed, you do קריעה. keriah. Okay, so now the גמרא
says like this, תנו רבנן: Tanu rabbanan: אחד השומע, Echad hashomeia, whether
you hear the blaspheming, ואחד שומע מפי שומע, ve'echad shomeia mipi shomeia,
even if you hear it secondhand. But we know that because the
דיינים dayanim heard it secondhand from the עדים. edim. Okay, so I
presumably that means that you've still heard the words. It's not like
somebody just said and reported, oh, so and so blasphemed God. You'd
have to say, so and so said X, Y, and Z, that
the words of the curse have to, presumably, would have to be
said. חייב לקרוע, Chayav likroia, and that you would get from the,
you know, from what happened here in the court case. והעדים אינם
חייבים לקרוע, Veha'edim einam chayavim likroia, but the עדים edim don't have
to do קריעה, keriah, שכבר קרעו בשעה ששמעו. shekevar kare'u besha'ah sheshame'u.
They already did it when they originally heard the case, when they
presumably that's what they did it when the original offense happened. So
the גמרא says, וכי קרעו בשעה ששמעו מאי הוי, vechi kare'u besha'ah
sheshame'u mai hava, so what? Why would that mean you wouldn't have
to do it again? הא קשמעי השתא, ha kashamei hashta, now they're
hearing it again. Maybe they should have to do it again. לא
סלקא דעתך, Lo salka daitach, that doesn't make sense, דכתיב, the verse
says, ויהי כשמוע המלך חזקיהו ויקרע את בגדיו. vayehi kishmoia hamelech Chizkiyahu
vayikra et begadov. When he heard what the words of רבשקה Ravshakeh
that רבשקה Ravshakeh had cursed God, he stood up and rent his
garment. So the גמרא says, המלך חזקיהו קרע, hamelech Chizkiyahu kara, it's
when the king tore his garments, והם, vehem, those that were reporting
it to him, לא קרעו, lo kare'u, did not tear. So once,
so if, you know, so if you've heard one person, for example,
curse God multiple times, you would have to do it multiple times.
But if you're repeating the event that you've already done קריעה keriah
for, you don't have to go ahead and do it a second
time. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehudah amar Shmuel, השומע
אזכרה מפי עובד כוכבים אינו חייב לקרוע. hashomeia azkarah mipi oved kochavim
einno chayav likroia. So we already said that a person isn't חייב
מיתה chayav mitah unless they use God's four letter name. Okay, there
was a whole discussion before whether בני נח have the same requirement
of God's explicit name, you know, using God's name to curse God's
name and so on. Okay, so but that's one question: what do
you have to do to be חייב מיתה? chayav mitah? But now,
what do you have to do in order to do קריעה? keriah?
Maybe it is a different standard than what has to be done
for it to be a sin of חייב מיתה. chayav mitah. So
he says even if you hear a non-Jew curse God even with
a כינוי, kinui, with like another name of God, right? By the
way, that would not include the words God damn because that's God
should curse something else. This is God being the cursed, cursing God.
Okay, even using some substitute word, okay, presumably even in an English
word, you would have to do קריעה. keriah. I'm sorry, אינו חייב
לקרוע, einno chayav likroia, you don't have to do קריעה. keriah. ואי
תימא רבשקה, Ve'i teima Ravshakeh, so why did they tear over רבשקה?
Ravshakeh? ישראל מומר היה, Yisrael mumar haya, that was not a non-Jew,
he was a Jewish apostate. But if you hear it from a
non-Jew, you don't have to do קריעה. keriah. Okay, it's not exactly
clear why, but presumably it's less seen as blaspheming because it's, you
know, we have a more intimate relationship with God, so the act
of cursing is seen as more of a, you know, of more
of a rupture. ואמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Ve'amar Rav Yehudah amar
Shmuel, אין קורעין אלא על שם המיוחד בלבד. ein korin ela al
shem hameyuchad bilvad. Similar to what you need to do to be
חייב מיתה, chayav mitah, even so, but he just said that you
have to hear from a Jew in order to do קריעה, keriah,
and similar to the חיוב מיתה, chiyuv mitah, it would have to
be using God's four letter name, God's explicit name. לאפוקי כינוי דלא,
Le'apokei kinui dela, if it was just a כינוי, kinui, whatever, no,
a substitute name for God, not. Okay, so according to him it's
a limited case you do קריעה, keriah, from a Jew, God's... explicit
name. ופליגי דרבי חייא בתרווייהו, U'pligi de'Rabbi Chiya bitravayhu, and that and
that argues on two points, but both of these points argue on
רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, דאמר רבי חייא, de'amar Rabbi Chiya, רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiya says, number one, השומע אזכרה בזמן הזה אינו חייב לקרוע,
hashomea azkara bazman hazeh eino chayav likroa, if somebody hears God's name,
presumably meaning in the context of being cursed, cursing God with a
with a with you know with one of God's other names, you
do not have to do קריעה, kriah, שאלמלא אתה אומר כן, she'ilmalei
atah omer kein, if you don't say that, נתמלאו כל הבגדים קרעים,
nitmalu kol hab'gadim k'raim, our garments will be filled with tears. The
non-Jews around us are always cursing out God. I don't know what
that context is that the non-Jews around you are always cursing out
God. But anyway, so now it says like this: ממאי? mimai? Now
who are you hearing this from? אילימא מישראל, ilima mi'Yisrael, if you're
hearing these curses all the time from Jews, מי פקירי כולי האי?
mi pakiri kulei hai? Since when are they so you know like
violate that Jews nowadays are always cursing out God? אלא פשיטא מעובד
כוכבים, ela peshita me'oved kochavim, it must mean the context is that
we're dealing with non-Jews. ואי שמא המיוחד, ve'ee shema ham'yuchad, and if
we're talking about God's explicit name, maybe that's what he's talking about,
מי גמירי? mi g'miri? Since when do they know how to say
God's explicit name? Okay, so you know, unique name. אלא לאו בכינוי?
ela lav b'kinui? So his context where he said non-Jews nowadays are
always hearing curses all the time, logically the only context for that
is non-Jews cursing God with one of the other names of God,
and nevertheless he says that the only reason we're exempt from doing
קריעה kriah is because it's so prevalent, but which would mean in
principle we should be doing קריעה. kriah. Okay, שמע מינה בזמן הזה
הוא דלא הא מעיקרא חייב שמע מינה, shma mina bazman hazeh hu
d'lo ha me'ikra chayav shma mina, so you see the exact opposite,
the first teaching of Rav Yehuda in the name of Shmuel was
it had to be a Jew and it had to be God's
explicit name, and this statement of who was it again, רבי חייא,
Rabbi Chiya, is that in principle even if you hear it from
a non-Jew and even another name of God you would have to
do קריעה, kriah, but but nowadays it's so prevalent that that's no
longer meaningful. Okay again, I don't know what the context is that
non-Jews were cursing God. I will say by the way on a
regular basis I will say that both of these statements by the
way notice they say השומע אזכרה, hashomea azkara, they say you hear
God's name being mentioned. It didn't say curse. Rashi says it means
God's name being cursed, right? Because it would be bizarre to think
that just because a non-Jew said God's name that would require a
Jew to do קריעה. kriah. Okay but it's also hard to imagine
that the non-Jews are cursing God right and left. Okay again when
somebody says people say like you know goddamn right and left but
again that's not cursing God, that's calling on God to curse something
else. Alright anyway moving on. השני אומר אף אני כמהו, hasheni omer
af ani kamoho, the second one says I heard just like him,
so he doesn't have to repeat it. אמר ריש לקיש שמע מינה
אף אני כמהו כשר בדיני ממונות ובדיני נפשות, amar Reish Lakish shma
mina af ani kamoho kasher b'dinei mamonot u'v'dinei nefashot, technically speaking if
one person said this is what I saw and the other witness
said yes me too, technically that would be considered giving your testimony.
Okay but ומהי דעבדי רבנן? u'mai de'avdi rabbanan? And generally the rabbis
demand more, they demand the second witness say it out explicitly. But
how do I know that technically that works? והכא כיון דלא אפשר
אוקמוה אדרבייתא, ve'hacha keivan d'lo efshar okmuha ad'raita, here since we didn't
want the second witness to repeat the curse, we let it go
by the real halacha which is it's enough to just say me
too. For עדות eidus you don't have to explicitly you know give
your testimony. דאי סלקא דעתך פסול, de'ee salka dach'tach pasul, if you
would think that this really doesn't count as testimony saying me too,
הכא משום דלא אפשר קטלינן לגברא? hacha mishum d'lo efshar katlinan l'gavra?
Just because we can't demand that the second witness say the curse
of God a second time,
so would that how could we execute this person? If we're executing
this person based on the witnesses' me too, you see that technically
me too works even if normally we don't accept it. Okay can't
they sit separately in the chamber and examine the witness? Yes they
do separate me too if you didn't hear the first. Oh no
no no but all that examining and whatever all that examining was...
sorry all that examining was like I mean here there was a
whole process where they said everything with but they said it with
euphemisms. Yosef's... I don't mean that this also applies to monetary and
capital cases. Right. So but in capital cases didn't we say that
they brought them... Yeah I think it's a good point like how
first of all that might not be required right that also might
not be you know that might be the Rabbinic requirement not the
Torah requirement. Um but also like I think there's a difference between
cross-examining them and so on and checking out their story and then
the official act of giving their testimony. So you know they could
be cross-examined and but the official act could be a me too.
But it's a good point but that might also not be the
minimum Torah standard. Okay. השלישי אומר אף אני כמהו סתמא כרבי עקיבא
דמקיש ג' לב'. hashlishi omer af ani kamoho stama k'Rabbi Akiva d'makish
gimmel l'bet. So the fact that we need to get the third
guy to say אף אני כמהו af ani kamoho shows we're working
with רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says that when
there are three witnesses right if any one of them is invalid
you throw it all out. So meaning why didn't we just stop
at two? Why did we make sure we wanted to get the
third guy to testify as well? Because once you have all the
witnesses there are consequences to that if one of them is found
in you know no good. Let's just at least turn the page
and read the so we can read a little of the behind
let's read the משנה. Mishna. Okay. So the Gemara says העובד עבודת
כוכבים אחד העובד. ha'oved avodat kochavim echad ha'oved. Interesting word המזבח, hamizabeach,
not זובח. zovayach. Okay, so now we're going on to the חיוב
סקילה. chiyuv skilah. We're moving away from blaspheming and we're going on
to worshiping foreign gods. So, whether it is, I won't call it
idolatry, worshiping foreign gods, whether you do, whether it's a worship or
whether it's slaughtering, sacrificing, slaughtering an animal, באחד המקטר be'echad hamikater
whether it is putting up incense or burning something on the altar,
ובאחד המנסך uve'echad hamenasech or whether it's pouring a libation on the
altar, ובאחד המשתחוה uve'echad hamishtachaveh whether it's prostrating, ובאחד המקבלו עליו לאלוה.
uve'echad hamikabelo alav l'eloah. And not only that, not only any of
those acts, but this last line is very important, even if somebody
just says, I accept you as my god. Okay, so first of
all, רש״י Rashi has an interesting question about whether it has to
be in front of the idol or even away from the idol.
רש״י Rashi sounds like even if you're not in the presence of
an idol because all you, you know, and somebody just says, I
accept this god as my god, like that would be an act
of עבודה זרה. avoda zara. You know, that's a little funny. עבודה
זרה avoda zara we normally think is an act of worship, right?
It might be an act of apostasy, it might be an act
of whatever, אלוהים אחרים, elohim acherim, you know, what is it? לא
יהיה לך אלוהים אחרים על פני. lo yihye lcha elohim acherim al
panai. Like, don't have another god. But that it's a prohibition of
לא תעשה, lo ta'aseh, worshipping, is pretty funny. It's also pretty important
because when the Jews were forcibly converted, right? Often it was just
a verbal acceptance of another religion, right? And it wasn't an act
of worship per se. So it's very interesting that this is included
in עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Like I said, it could be לא
יהיה לך אלוהים אחרים, lo yihye lcha elohim acherim, don't have any
other gods. But why this is an עבודה, avoda, you know, maybe
רש״י, Rashi, I think רש״י Rashi said, well, this is classic way
God is worshiped. The first way that you worship the God is
accepting the God as your god. But that's interesting. Okay. ואומר לו
אלי אתה. ve'omer lo eli ata. So A, accepted as a god,
and B, you say you are my god. So רש״י Rashi says
the double phrase here, aren't those the same? Is that מקבלו עליו
לאלוה m'kabelo alav l'eloah is even not in its presence. אלי אתה
eli ata is in its presence and you're pointing to the idol
and saying, you are my god. Okay,
אבל המגפף והמנשק, aval hamgafef v'hamnashek, but if it's other forms of
adoration which are not formal acts of worship, right, hugging and kissing,
והמכבד והמרבץ, v'hamchabed v'hamrabets, you know, sweeping in front of it or,
you know, whatever, מרבץ mrabets like settling the dust, והמרחץ והסך, v'hamrachets
v'hasach, or you wash it or you anoint oil on it, והמלביש
והמנעיל, v'hamalbish v'haman'il, or you clothe it or you put shoes on
it, עובר בלא תעשה, over b'lo ta'aseh, you transgress a negative prohibition,
okay, but of ולא
תעשה כמעשיהם, v'lo ta'aseh k'ma'aseihem, רש״י Rashi says comes to include, ולא
תעשה כמעשיהם, v'lo ta'aseh k'ma'aseihem, that comes to include even forms of
עבודה, avoda, even things which are not technical עבודה, avoda, but more
these acts of adoration. Okay, that's included. But it's not חייב מיתה.
chayav misa. חייב מיתה chayav misa has to be a classic formal
of worship, or we'll see more about that in the גמרא. הנודר
בשמו והמקיים בשמו, hanoder bishmo v'hakyayem bishmo,
if somebody takes a vow or an oath in the name of
a god, which is a common thing that, you know, believers do,
they swear in the name of their gods. So עובר בלא תעשה,
over b'lo ta'aseh, it's a negative prohibition but not חייב מיתה. chayav
misa. The negative prohibition is שם אלוהים אחרים לא תזכירו לא ישמע
על פיך. shem elohim acherim lo tazkiru lo yishama al picha.
The name of foreign gods should not be heard on your lips.
Okay, and that doesn't mean just saying the name of a foreign
god, but certainly what it means is don't use the name of
another god in a, in like, you know, in a meaningful way.
Don't swear by the name of another god or take an oath
by the name of another god. Okay, so these are things which
are negative prohibitions, these acts of adoration and swearing and taking an
oath, but they're not actual acts of worship and therefore they're not
punishable by death. Okay, and now here's two examples of the top
of the משנה mishna mentioned classic forms of worship, slaughtering, burning on
an altar, libations, prostrating.
The end of the משנה mishna mentioned acts of worship that are
unique to that god, even if they're not classic forms. הפוער עצמו
לבעל פעור, hapo'er atzmo l'ba'al pe'or, somebody who basically exposes himself and
defecates in front of בעל פעור, ba'al pe'or, presumably that was the
form of worship, זו היא עבודתו, zo hi avodato, that is its
form of worship and that's חייב מיתה. chayav misa. הזורק אבן למרקוליס,
hazorek even l'markolis, if somebody threw a stone to the מרקוליס markolis
which was these three stones, apparently it was like a god of
the, of like, of travel or of, you know, of the highways
or something like that.
You ever drive after New York to, to a Washington, to, to
Maryland, there's always I pass like a church that says Our Lady
of the Highways, anyway they got a whole statue up in front
of it. Anyway, so מרקוליס markolis was this god for like travelers
and the highways and so on, and what they do is they
throw a stone at this little three stone configuration, two at the
bottom and one at top. זו היא עבודתו. zo hi avodato. You
would think that all these acts are acts of degrading acts. No,
if this is the way it's worshiped, it's the way it's worshiped.
So either the unique way in which it's worshiped or standard forms
of worship is עבודה זרה avoda zara and accepting as a god,
other things are not עבודה זרה avoda zara but they might be
negative prohibitions. Okay, so we will pick up. Even from on top,
זוהי עבודתה. Zohi Avodatah. You would think that all these acts are
acts of degrading acts. No, if this is the way it's worshipped,
it's the way it's worshipped. So either the unique way in which
it's worshipped or standard forms of worship are עבודה זרה Avoda Zarah
and accepting as a god, other things are not עבודה זרה Avoda
Zarah but they might be negative prohibitions. Okay, so we will pick
up with this tomorrow.